window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Data_Structure - Data_Structure — Slot 14 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Data_Structure — Slot 14",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>An array X of n distinct integers is interpreted as a complete binary tree. The index of the first element of the array is 0. If only the root node does not satisfy the heap property, the algorithm to convert the complete binary tree into a heap has the best asymptotic time complexity of <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O (n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O (\\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O (n \\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O (n \\log \\log n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O (\\log n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3616/gate2006-it-72\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>An array X of n distinct integers is interpreted as a complete binary tree. The index of the first element of the array is 0. The index of the parent of element\\(X[i], i \\neq 0\\), is? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\left \\lfloor \\dfrac i 2 \\right \\rfloor\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\left \\lceil \\dfrac{i-1}{2} \\right \\rceil\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\left \\lceil \\dfrac i 2 \\right \\rceil\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\left \\lceil \\dfrac i 2 \\right \\rceil - 1\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\left \\lceil \\dfrac i 2 \\right \\rceil - 1\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3615/gate2006-it-71\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Suppose that we have numbers between 1 and 100 in a binary search tree and want to search for the number 55. Which of the following sequences CANNOT be the sequence of nodes examined? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>{10,75,64,43,60,57,55}</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>{90,12,68,34,62,45,55}</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>{9,85,47,68,43,57,55}</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>{79,14,72,56,16,53,55}</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>{9,85,47,68,43,57,55}</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3588/gate2006-it-45\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following sequences of array elements forms a heap? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>{23,17,14,6,13,10,1,12,7,5}</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>{23,17,14,6,13,10,1,5,7,12}</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>{23,17,14,7,13,10,1,5,6,12}</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>{23,17,14,7,13,10,1,12,5,7}</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>{23,17,14,7,13,10,1,5,6,12}</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3587/gate2006-it-44\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>In a binary tree, the number of internal nodes of degree 1 is 5, and the number of internal nodes of degree 2 is 10. The number of leaf nodes in the binary tree is <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>10</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>11</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>12</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>15</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>11</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3548/gate2006-it-9\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>A 3-ary max heap is like a binary max heap, but instead of 2 children, nodes have 3 children. A 3-ary heap can be represented by an array as follows: The root is stored in the first location, a[0], nodes in the next level, from left to right, is stored from a[1] to a[3]. The nodes from the second level of the tree from left to right are stored from a[4] location onward. An item x can be inserted into a 3-ary heap containing n items by placing x in the location a[n] and pushing it up the tree to satisfy the heap property. <br><br>Suppose the elements 7, 2, 10 and 4 are inserted, in that order, into the valid 3-ary max heap found in the above question, Which one of the following is the sequence of items in the array representing the resultant heap? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>10, 7, 9, 8, 3, 1, 5, 2, 6, 4</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>10, 9, 8, 7, 6, 5, 4, 3, 2, 1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>10, 9, 4, 5, 7, 6, 8, 2, 1, 3</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>10, 8, 6, 9, 7, 2, 3, 4, 1, 5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>10, 7, 9, 8, 3, 1, 5, 2, 6, 4</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/87191/gate2006-77#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>A 3-ary max heap is like a binary max heap, but instead of 2 children, nodes have 3 children. A 3-ary heap can be represented by an array as follows: The root is stored in the first location, a[0], nodes in the next level, from left to right, is stored from a[1] to a[3]. The nodes from the second level of the tree from left to right are stored from a[4] location onward. An item x can be inserted into a 3-ary heap containing n items by placing x in the location a[n] and pushing it up the tree to satisfy the heap property. <br><br> Which one of the following is a valid sequence of elements in an array representing 3-ary max heap? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1, 3, 5, 6, 8, 9</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>9, 6, 3, 1, 8, 5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>9, 3, 6, 8, 5, 1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>9, 5, 6, 8, 3, 1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>9, 5, 6, 8, 3, 1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1852/gate2006-76#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Given two arrays of numbers \\(a_{1},...,a_{n}\\) and \\(b_{1},...,b_{n}\\) where each number is 0 or 1,\nthe fastest algorithm to find the largest span(i,j) such that \\(a_{i}+a_{i+1}+...+a_{j}=b_{i}+b_{i+1}+.....+b_{j}\\) , or report that there is no such span, <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Takes \\(O(3^{n})\\) and \\(\\Omega (2^{n})\\) time if hashing is permitted</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Takes \\(O(n^{3})\\) and \\(\\Omega (n^{2.5})\\) time in the key comparison model</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Takes \\(\\Theta (n)\\) time and space</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Takes \\(O(\\sqrt{n})\\) time only if the sum of the 2n elements is an even number</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Takes \\(\\Theta (n)\\) time and space</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1832/gate2006-54#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>An implementation of a queue Q, using two stacks S1 and S2, is given below:<pre><code>\nvoid insert(Q,x){\n    push (S1,x);\n}\nvoid delete(Q){\n   if (stack-empty (S2))then\n         if (stack-empty (S1))then{\n               print(\"Q is empty\");\n               return;\n           }\n         else while (! (stack-empty)(S1)){\n                x=pop(S1);\n                push(S2,x);\n            }\n       x=pop(S2);\n}</code></pre> Let n insert and m(\\(\\leq\\)n) delete operations be performed in an arbitrary on an\nempty queue Q, Let x and y be the number of push and pop operations performed\nrespectively in the processes. Which one of the following is true for all m and n ? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(m+n \\leq x\\leq 2n\\) and \\(2m \\leq y \\leq n+m\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(m+n \\leq x\\leq 2n\\) and \\(2m \\leq y \\leq 2n\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(2m\\leq x\\leq 2n\\) and \\(2m \\leq y \\leq n+m\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2m \\leq x\\leq 2n\\) and \\(2m \\leq y \\leq 2n\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(m+n \\leq x\\leq 2n\\) and \\(2m \\leq y \\leq n+m\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1826/gate2006-49#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>An element in an array X is called a leader if it is grater than all elements to the\nright of it in X. The best algorithm to find all leaders in an array. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Solves it in linear time using a left to right pass of the array</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Solves in linear time using a right to left pass of the array</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Solves it is using divide and conquer in time \\(\\Theta\\)(nlogn)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Solves it in time \\(\\Theta (n^{2})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Solves in linear time using a right to left pass of the array</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/978/gate2006-17#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>A scheme for storing binary trees in an array X is as follows. Indexing of X starts\nat 1 instead of 0. The roots is stored at X[1]. For a node stored at X[i], the left\nchild, if any, is stored in X[2i] and the right child, if any, in X[2i + 1]. To be able\nto store any binary tree on n vertices, the minimum size of X should be <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>log n</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>n</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2n+1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2^{n}-1\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(2^{n}-1\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/974/gate2006-13#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>In a binary max heap containing n numbers, the smallest element can be found in time <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2006)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (log logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (1)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/889/gate2006-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Let a and b be two sorted arrays containing n integers each, in non-decreasing order. Let c be a sorted array containing 2n integers obtained by merging the two arrays a and b. Assuming the arrays are indexed starting from 0, consider the following four statements<br><br>\nI. \\(a[i] \\geq b [i] \\Rightarrow c[2i] \\geq a [i]\\)<br>\nII. \\(a[i] \\geq b [i] \\Rightarrow c[2i] \\geq b [i]\\)<br>\nIII. \\(a[i] \\geq b [i] \\Rightarrow c[2i] \\leq a [i]\\)<br>\nIV. \\(a[i] \\geq b [i] \\Rightarrow c[2i] \\leq b [i]\\)<br><br>\nWhich of the following is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>only I and II</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>only I and IV</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>only II and III</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>only III and IV</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>only II and III</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3820/gate2005-it-59\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>A binary search tree contains the numbers 1,2,3,4,5,6,7,8. When the tree is traversed in pre-order and the values in each node printed out, the sequence of values obtained is 5,3,1,2,4,6,8,7. If the tree is traversed in post-order, the sequence obtained would be <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>8,7,6,5,4,3,2,1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>1,2,3,4,8,7,6,5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2,1,4,3,6,7,8,5</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2,1,4,3,7,8,6,5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>2,1,4,3,7,8,6,5</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3816/gate2005-it-55\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>The following C function takes a singly-linked list of integers as a parameter and rearranges the elements of the list. The list is represented as pointer to a structure. The function is called with the list containing the integers 1,2,3,4,5,6,7 in the given order. What will be the contents of the list after the function completes execution? <br><pre><code> struct node {int value; struct node *next;);\nvoid rearrange (struct node *list) {\n    struct node *p, *q;\n    int temp;\n    if (!list || !list -&gt; next) return;\n    p = list; q = list -&gt; next;\n    while (q) {\n        temp = p -&gt; value;\n        p -&gt; value = q -&gt; value;\n        q -&gt; value = temp;\n        p = q -&gt; next;\n        q = p ? p -&gt; next : 0;\n      }\n}</code></pre> <br><br><strong>(GATE IT 2005)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>1,2,3,4,5,6,7</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>2,1,4,3,6,5,7</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>1,3,2,5,4,7,6</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>2,3,4,5,6,7,1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>2,1,4,3,6,5,7</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/3815/gate2005-it-54\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
